[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is from the Samyutta Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bhikkhus, suppose a foolish, incompetent, unskillful cook was to serve a king or his minister with a vast array of curries, superbly sour and bitter, pungent and sweet, hot and mild, salty and bland.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that cook didn't pick up the hint or the sign of his own master.
[SPEAKER_00]: Today, my master preferred this sauce,
[SPEAKER_00]: That foolish, incompetent, unskillful cook doesn't get presented with clothes, wages or bonuses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he doesn't pick up the hint of his own master.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, a foolish, incompetent, unskillful bhikkhu abides maintaining perspective of the body concurrently with the body, diligent, aware, and recollected, having subdued, longing, and upset in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: As he may, sorry, as he abides maintaining perspective of the body concurrently with the body, his mind does not become composed, and the defilements are not given up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't pick up the hint of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it goes on for the other satipaṭṭhāna, feelings, mind and phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the sutta continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: That foolish, incompetent and skillful bhikkhu doesn't gain pleasant abidings right in the present experience, nor does he gain recollection and awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that foolish, incompetent, unskillful bhikkhu does not pick up the hint of his own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose an astute, competent, skillful cook was to serve a ruler or their minister with a vast array of curries, superbly sour, bitter, pungent and sweet, hot and mild, salty and bland, and that cook
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, then it says, in the same way, a wise, competent, skillful bhikkhu abides maintaining perspective of the body concurrently with the body,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it goes on for the other satipaṭṭhāna in the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first thing that stands out to me is that this is talking about bhikkhus, about the skillful and unskillful bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, secondly, that both the skillful and the unskillful bhikkhu, eh... what does it say?
[SPEAKER_00]: They both must have understood, to some degree, yoniso, manasikāra, because they are abiding
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, body concurrently with body, feeling concurrently with feeling, and we have already given up longing for the world, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the case for both the skillful and the unskillful bhikkhu.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, talking about the hint or the sign of the mind, what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: That prevents him from gaining the right composure and giving up the defilements, as it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: What would you say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the most direct way of explaining is that if you don't see the sign of the mind, you don't see the defilements to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't see what you have to abandon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing is, as it says, you abandon longing and upset in regards to the world, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's already an achievement, of course, but... and it wouldn't have been accomplished without the prerequisites of virtue and sense restraint, which are there, because it's saying that it's a big group.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in regards to the world,
[SPEAKER_01]: That is one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, you could say there's longing and aversion in regard to your own mental states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that part isn't going to be easily abandoned just because you keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't want anything in the world, you don't depend on any external pleasures, you don't seek sensuality, you don't act out of aversion and all these things, you can still have a
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to your own mental states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the defilements are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they can't be abandoned accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's only when you see the sign of the mind that you would be able to do... Well, when you see the sign of the mind, which is where the defilements are, that you would be able to do anything about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you suddenly find yourself
[SPEAKER_01]: You just got another experience that doesn't... that happens not to provoke your defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: A peaceful state of mind or whatever that just happens... circumstantially happens not to provoke your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's give a concrete example.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as it's saying there, it's... Yeah, so, one of the things that stands out is that both of them are actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Like he hasn't been given the right instruction or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or he doesn't have the right meditation object.
[SPEAKER_01]: What it's saying is that both of them are attempting to do the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're attempting to be mindful of the body, feelings, mind, and dhammas, or phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not, in and of itself, what makes it wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that just because you're reflecting on the body, which is already, I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing the body concurrently with the body, that's already a step ahead of what most people will be doing in their meditation practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't even be doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be focusing on the body, focusing on particular sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, basically, you regard the body as an object in front of you, that you can focus on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Growing out of that is already a step forward, from where most people are, and that would put you in the position of this
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not even through yoniso manasikāra, just by changing your views, by recognizing that, you know, the defilements will never be on the level of objects and any effort that you might be putting into that will necessarily
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just by recognizing that, you know, any amount of focusing you might do, there's perfectly, like, space there for the dhammas to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you're focusing, that already shows you that
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just by going out of that and recognizing, okay, no, I'm supposed to be seeing the nature of my experiences, while those experiences are happening, within, obviously, the container of virtue and sensory strain, not just out there in the world trying to be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you recognize that, but even then, that you can still have these background unrecognized attitudes there, and that's where the sign of the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have, let's say, you're contemplating something you read from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're contemplating the impermanence of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're contemplating the nature of feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're contemplating anything, basically, that's in its
[SPEAKER_01]: It's content is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a good object.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the problem is wholesomeness, as I think we described in one of the previous talks, is never defined by what you're attending to, but the content of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the wholesomeness, or the greed, aversion, delusion, or absence of it, that you would have there, is defined by what is your mind's attitude
[SPEAKER_01]: Towards that contemplation you're doing, that's where you would find the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... the same object is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that you change something different.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, let's say that these peripheral kind of meanings that are floating there, in relation to what you're attending to, and what will be one of the most relevant examples for people,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be the sense of anticipation, expectation and craving for special experiences and insights to arise out of the meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be doing the same practice, the same wholesome
[SPEAKER_01]: contemplation and reflection that you read from the suttas, but with that taken-for-granted background of anticipation and desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't see that actually your contemplation should be applying to that, not just robotically continuing to focus on the... well, it's not even focus anymore, it's a contemplation, factually, like it says he's doing it properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because he fails to include that into the picture as well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the defilement won't be abandoned, because it will never be abandoned accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be seen in order to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can do that practice for a hundred years, then the defilement continues to float there, and it's never going to go away by itself, unless you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are we saying that these background attitudes that you just described, that that is basically synonymous with the defilement?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like you will never...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the foundations, they will be, let's say, confirmed or cemented by things in the foreground that you can attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, you have a sensual state of mind and you are also actively proliferating sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, that's a whole
[SPEAKER_01]: But because of the state of mind, that's what defines, not the presence of those images in your mind, but the attitude of the mind towards it, is what defines that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, I mean, you can be thinking about the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even in your ordinary experience, an ordinary person who doesn't practice, they can see, on some occasions, I can be having exactly the same perceptions in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on other occasions, the same thing is there, and there is lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the content of the experience were all that is relevant to define whether a department is there, that wouldn't be the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you have these specific objects, you would have lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: And only then would you be able to justify an object observation practice, because then it would mean
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody, let's say, sits down, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: They notice there's a sensual thought present, but then now you're saying that the actual hindrance of sensuality is not just the presence of that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, it's
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, not just even the thought, just, you could say, in regard to feelings in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example, that monk there, it's saying it's abandoned, he has abandoned already, longing and aversion in regard to the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, he's not having particular sensual thoughts anymore, because that requires active volition.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he would have already abandoned that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But behind his efforts at that time to purify his mind, he didn't see that there is still these more subtle implications to that same practice that he's doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That he needs to... he needs to start including that as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: In his renunciation, in order for the mind to be actually purified, it's not enough just to not be having sensual thoughts or aversive thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's usually where people would then sort of like jump the gun, so to say, where they see, okay, so I stopped having these
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I'm not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_01]: The defilements are clearly still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still liable to greed, aversion, and delusion, even though I have stopped acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am perfectly restrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what you need to do there now is
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exactly the opposite direction of seeing the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like actively ignoring the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start...
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem with that is, that will never be something that you achieve overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those signs of the mind
[SPEAKER_01]: It will never be like a sudden epiphany that comes up for you one day.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be... it is necessarily a gradual development.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's starting to notice your own intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically what it comes down to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's intentions, not in the sense of decisions, which is what people usually... Like, you could say... you could present the concept that we're talking about, you could present it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: These impurities, these defilements, that you would get to see when you see the signs of the mind, they're still intentional.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it's happening by itself, but it is on a much more subtle level than what you're generally used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the discernment of that, basically, like pulling you pulling you back in the beginning, all you see is these very coarse actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you have to start with the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in the beginning, the only thing a person can be sure about is that breaking the precepts is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you... that's why it's a graduate training.
[SPEAKER_01]: You work through that, and then these more subtle layers of the same principles start to be revealed, up to the point where you can see your own attitude in regard to your own thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the thoughts themselves, but your attitude in regard to those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, like, it's not that the... you know, it's not that the presence of an attractive person in front of you
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... engaging with the person intentionally, for sensual reasons, that is sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that same principle, you... you eventually bring it
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the presence of these things that is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your attitude in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, it's not something you'll be able to figure it out... figure it out overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... it's a... by maintaining that... that container of virtual and sensory strength, it's like a... like a... like a fence that you put around your mind, and then the suffering that's left there, that forces you to deal with it a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not you... again, not... not in the sense of find the answer suddenly,
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, it's leaving you no choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if you refrain from trying to take a shortcut and going into the route of absorption and distraction, it will force you to start recognizing, as it says there, what is it that I'm feeding... why is it that the king is still not pleased?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's go into that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But maybe we won't step back still, because
[SPEAKER_00]: So, perhaps we should clear that up first, before we go and discuss the seven in some detail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, there's there's another citta that's quite relevant, that says, um, I think it's Saṅgha Charnikaya 668, and it says,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, without learning to... a monk who delights in seclusion, he won't be able to... A monk who's not able to delight in seclusion, he won't be able to see his signs in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: A monk who cannot see his signs in the mind, he won't be able to get the right
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is it then that seclusion is necessary for seeing the side of the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's another fence.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the the most...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're in seclusion...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're in seclusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just being seclusion, it's actually preferring seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's inconceivable that you'll be able to be at ease in seclusion and generally prefer it, if you haven't established these prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even in the suttas, it's shown monks who hadn't developed themselves enough, they would go into seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the first thing that would start arising is sensual thoughts, aversive thoughts, and all sorts of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing is, like, again, because the whole shortcut of meditation techniques comes in, people actually don't realize what the baseline of their mind would be when they go into seclusion, if they don't start distracting themselves in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually how you would be able to know
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have developed these prerequisites enough, like, when you go into seclusion, and you don't do... like, you don't do anything, but you also don't actively try not to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not trying to suppress your thoughts, you're not just
[SPEAKER_01]: There, you start to see whether there's a certain stability to the mind, naturally, in that open environment, like half-open, half-closed, let's say, or whether, you know, it started going all over the place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that tells you that you won't be, like, your prerequisites are still insufficient for you to be able to delight in true solution.
[SPEAKER_01]: Generally, not distracting yourself, even with your meditation and all these things, because something that distracts you cannot be rightly called meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is already, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first of all, seclusion has to be understood, like no presence of other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what seclusion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cannot equate that with your effort to lay between.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seclusion means on your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, somewhere door closed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because as soon as other people are present,
[SPEAKER_01]: Certain attitudes, again on that same background level, they almost inevitably are going to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will not have the capacity to see those attitudes and question them, because they're so deeply ingrained, that it's almost as if they're automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not, ultimately.
[SPEAKER_01]: So an arahant wouldn't have those attitudes after, you know, having finished the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: But
[SPEAKER_01]: For you, starting from the beginning, it's like, you know, eh... it's almost like lifting a heavy weight.
[SPEAKER_01]: For somebody who's not strong enough, there's no way that they won't be doing it with bad form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though technically it's not absolutely necessary, you could lift the weight with good form.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this case, practically speaking, it's not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to actually withdraw yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... like, when you're in seclusion, that will allow you to, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Have more space to to actually start questioning these attitudes in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Including the attitudes of whatever meditation instruction you have received.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now the question is why are you even going to do something formal when you have already been keeping precepts, practicing sense restraint and are observing the body's occlusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because that's how it's going to be probably for most people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would already betray a view that, you know, you think you
[SPEAKER_01]: Why do I want to do this in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that in itself could be a defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, like, if you ran with it, with that intention, from the start, nothing that comes up, again, as I said, a hundred years after doing that practice, will undo the fact that you took a wrong turn from the start.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... eh... the... the... all the insights that you would get from
[SPEAKER_01]: They're on the level of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's precisely, like, you know, what you would read as all these experiences of a, you know, a flash of consciousness arising and ceasing and all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all of that is just sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the sign of the mind is not a sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even a specific thought that you catch or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, a discernment of the attitude in regard to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it means seeing your mind, which is always necessarily a peripheral phenomenon, seeing that as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas before, obviously, it's there, but you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's called the sign or nimitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, I translated it as hint.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are associations of, you know, you're meditating and this nimitta comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be while you're expecting for this thing to come up, seeing that attitude in yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's not that... Obviously, it's not that catching it, you know, magically solved the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Catching the signs of the mind allows you to do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that... that's... that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, let's make a move from here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, suppose...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's two things we can do.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can either unpack the simile and see which ingredients are there, in order to make sure that we understand this simile properly, and then we can clear up what is the actual work to be done, once the sign of the mind is already discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the simile is... is actually, you know, whenever you see something in the suttas like that,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't just kind of impose your notions on it, but actually you step back and see if the Buddha chose that simile, it must be for a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this case, what is the similarity between this principle we've been describing of the sign of the mind as an indirect thing that cannot be directly observed as a sense object and the preferences of the king
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically the fact that he doesn't tell you, I want this or I want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't make a gesture with his hands or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's indirect.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it says, he took a lot of this
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even deliberately, just by failing to actually discern those signs, he will be thinking, oh, this food is... everyone likes it, so I'm just gonna cook this, because, you know, who doesn't like chocolate cake or something?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he ignores the fact that the rightness of the dish depends on the cook, not on what you think
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, like, you read something from the suttas, you assume that that in itself, just doing that, is going to make it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, if that's not what the cook needs, or what the king wants, it's not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it's the best dish in the world, that everybody else would like,
[SPEAKER_01]: For him, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what does king stand for in the simile?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the the... but again, that's the clarification that needs to be made, because sometimes people read that simile
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, you would be failing to question the fact that the reason why you're suffering is because there's craving right then and there as a sign that you're not discerning, and that if you were to just address that, you would actually fix the problem without having to fabricate or give rise to anything secondary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's what you're feeding the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, again, like, oh, today I have to do breath meditation because, you know, I feel like it's... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that's what's gonna please the mind most.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's any of these things, any of these meditations or
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not in itself... like, the meditation in itself is not what's right or wrong, as I just said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... what is the, let's say, counterattitude that's associated with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are... what you're feeding the king, let's say, is... you're either going with it... let's say there's a... there's an essential tendency or a craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your...
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentions, the intentions that you exert, will either be going with the grain, or against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember that tendency.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, if you don't know, 100%, that they are going against the grain, they're going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... What you're feeding the mind, quote-unquote, really, is the intention behind your contemplation, not the contemplation itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why in the suttas, you have all these different, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: None of the approaches that you can take, and none of them is more special than the other in and of themselves, because what will make them work, quote-unquote, is the attitude with which you pack it together, let's say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's always going to be two components.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you know, if you're just reflecting on, I don't know, some random
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to some extent, yes, it has to be something from the suttas, but there's two components to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's your attitude behind it and the contemplation itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where... that is really what you're feeding the king.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what... and you feed the king what he needs
[SPEAKER_01]: Only if you can see where is it that he's inclining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you know what is it that needs to be actually addressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the same contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that, like, I need to do another one now, because the mind is like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, you know, sometimes people think, oh, if I essentially desire, I need to do a sūla.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I have aversion, I need to do a mettā.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I have this, I need to counter it with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not, that's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could do the same contemplation for everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will all depend on seeing where the craving is and using that contemplation as a means to, let's say, re-establish the right perspective that starts or teases to provide fuel for that craving, which you need to see before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, practically speaking, those contemplations, that's where people allow them to see that background attitude most clearly,
[SPEAKER_00]: That will be, for them, the best way to go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the less abstract or intellectual the contemplation is, because that's all in the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to pick up a theme or a contemplation that has the highest chance that it's not going to be disconnected from that background attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: In fact, the whole contemplation should go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, again, it wouldn't be... where we would make it right or wrong would be that
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that contemplation, you would be able to bundle it together with the right attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, yeah, for different people, there will be different things that will be more suitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the suttas would say, for those who have a strong tendency towards defilements, you know, these contemplations of death, and the subha, and all these things, they would be more beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, not because... if you do it
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, you can still be dealing with an attitude of craving against these thoughts that are arising by themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not willing to endure them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not willing to see that they arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then your attitude, your responsibilities is the light in those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just want to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you keep doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Blindly, with that background attitude, even though technically the object of a subha is wholesome, for you at that time, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not seeing that actually the king is... what the king needs is not to get rid of these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that attitude of the light that needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, that's what would make any contemplation right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not working.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it says, the mind is not becoming composed.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dhammas are not being abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pressure is increasing, not decreasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're getting even more agitated than before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't change it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: It will still not work on the level that it should, unless you start seeing the attitude behind that's making it not work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the contemplation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your, kind of, unquestioned attitudes that are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, kind of, the suffering that comes up, and that's why, again, going back to seclusion and so on, when you're in seclusion and your mind is, kind of, going everywhere,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's another thing, actually, we should clarify before we go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're in seclusion, the whole point is to allow your mind to move to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be, you know, bottling it up into this or that, kind of, overly controlled mental environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, you basically, within the precepts, within that environment, you allow your mind to move and then, even thinking about
[SPEAKER_01]: random things, as long as it's not obviously unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there, you're going to be able to see that's going to reveal the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the suffering is not in your mind thinking about those things, it's in the attitude while those thoughts are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where that's where then you will be forced to start addressing
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a certainty that that was the only way to actually deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could have distracted yourself with something that would have temporarily suppressed the symptoms, but that would have been basically just useless.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the end, it doesn't help.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so now, okay, suppose somebody is in seclusion, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Meeting all these prerequisites that we have discussed so far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, what's next?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: What next?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you already saw that those thoughts are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already not giving in to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recollect, okay, well, this body is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any inclination that I may have to indulge in the objects that belong to this body will make me even more liable to suffer when that body breaks apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as the mind doesn't, again, start delighting in essential thoughts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so then, well, then you're overlooking some other background attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not seeing now the attitude of expectation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just running towards this experience you think you should have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's actually the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether the experience comes later on or whatever, you still didn't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, you were suffering to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not really solving the liabilities of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you notice the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You notice the inclination of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it then said, the suttas would then say, your job is then not to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the satipaṭṭhāna sutta itself says, actually, he knows
[SPEAKER_01]: Lustful mind is lustful mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows averse mind is averse mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows distracted mind is distracted mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... Yeah, that's defined as purity, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... you basically... for as long as you don't lose sight of that, and you will lose sight of that when you either fall again back into the sense objects, or
[SPEAKER_01]: You fall too much into the side of denying them and trying to replace them with other thoughts that you think are better.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to stay in the middle, which is, you're not delighting in the thoughts, but you're also not trying to replace them with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, to that extent, you're seeing the side of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's inextricably tied the middle way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not getting rid of the mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's knowing it for what it is, and then not adding fuel to the unwholesome states that are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when the mind is in the... it obviously works the opposite way as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is in a wholesome state, let's say, when the five energies have been abandoned, you also know that for yourself, and you know exactly how it came about.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because the whole time you were aware of the king's preferences, and you were doing the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now,
[SPEAKER_01]: The king is pleased, and you know exactly how to maintain that, and there is nobody in the world that can suddenly make you lose that which you worked for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, when people say, oh, I lost my samādhi or something, that's because they didn't have it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see the signs in the mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no way except your own intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if it is right samādhi to begin with, which happens on the basis of seeing the side of the mind, there is nothing except your own intention which can, you know, make it decrease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the... you could basically say, as a kind of illustration, slightly
[SPEAKER_01]: Wherever you're looking at, even mentally, whenever you're directing your beam of attention, if you want to put it that way, the side of the mind is what's around that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Around that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the same way I'm looking here now, and the back of my head, like, I know that there's stuff back there, but I can't directly look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, while I'm looking at outside, I know that there's stuff back there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might know, let's say, that, you know, there's something behind my head, and if I lean too far back, I'm going to hit my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not directly looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's... that could be one practical way of... of... because if you try to turn towards it, well, now, see, the back of my head remains the back of my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will never change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is this the recollection and awareness aspect?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, that's another thing that says it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without seeing the center of the mind, you don't have recollection and awareness, even though you might be...
[SPEAKER_01]: you don't see the side of the mind, you don't have recollection and awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not awareness of... like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's even a... like a... like a... it doesn't even make sense to call observation of one object awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when the suttas say, what is awareness?
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, a monk is aware of his thoughts as they arise, as they endure, as they cease, and his feelings as they arise, as they endure, as they cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you actually see those things as objects?
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole point is, no, you can't, because those things are...
[SPEAKER_01]: In order to... you can see the thoughts themselves are objects, of course, but your knowledge of those things is not on the level of objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's a general principle of knowledge, in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does a car mechanic
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I might have given that example before.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows all the inner workings of the car and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That knowledge is not a sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were, you just show that to somebody else and he would have exactly the same knowledge the car mechanic does.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's one practical way of thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always behind your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the principle of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's important not to mystify it and think that it's not a phenomenon or it's hidden in my experience or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like the back of my head doesn't exist, or like what's behind me doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that if I focus too much on what's in front of me, I forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot sustain that knowledge of the backgrounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to the extent that you lose yourself in all this in front, you will be compromising that background knowledge, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, in front can be on the most basic level sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, but you can even
[SPEAKER_01]: In front would even count as, you know, your ideas about the dhamma, and your notions, and your effort towards it, and your striving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That becomes in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then behind that, there's a whole range of attitudes, and cravings, and expectations, that if you're not actively making an effort to recognize, they will be driving that whole endeavor, and means
[SPEAKER_01]: It's content might be present there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not actually done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because there's a relationship between mind, citta, and cetanā, which means intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, they're actually derived from the same root.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mind really is... it's... that's why, again, it's also not just something you catch as some sort of independent object, like you would catch a vision of something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the best simile, because it's kind of instantaneous, whereas I've been saying the side of the mind is something that's developed gradually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will never have a sudden insight where your recognition goes from 10% to 90% in one night.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it serves to illustrate with, like, you know, you see your nails,
[SPEAKER_01]: In your fingers and stuff, and, you know, they're kind of very... you see that even though you're not cutting your nails, for some reason, they're always very short.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, at some point, you figure out that you catch yourself biting your nails.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, actually, your nails were in that condition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're self-experiencing the suffering as a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's causing that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's these intentions that you don't see.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where the sign of the mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it would be... slowly, you get to see, through the evolution of the gradual training... See, that sign of the mind is... has to be present throughout, even from the very start with the virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the extent of it is getting refined.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even just to keep the five precepts, like, to keep them in their spirits, you can keep the rules, you know, the letter of the rules, mechanically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But to be able to keep the rules in their spirit, you would already have to have a basic recognition of the side of the mind, because, you know, let's say, lying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you don't discern your intention,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you're saying what you're saying to another person, there might be cases where you're not necessarily telling an outright lie, but you're intentionally misrepresenting the truth, because it's just too unpleasant to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, or, you know, you might be keeping even, let's say, the eight precepts, and the precept on entertainment, let's say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you might, in various occasions, come across
[SPEAKER_01]: News, whatever, videos, newspapers and stuff, or you might be using the internet for some practical purpose, but unless you're able to see that intention behind, so why is it that I'm actually choosing to do this right now, you would be unable to really know whether you're actually refraining from entertainment or not, because anything can become entertainment, just like anything can be
[SPEAKER_01]: A way of distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to see what the suttas define as grasping the signs and features of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be able to see that, nor would you be able to see that non-universion that would arise on account of that grasping of signs and features, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, the watchfulness and vigilance
[SPEAKER_01]: Purifying your mind from obstructive states, that would already be fully contingent on seeing the sign of the mind, because otherwise you don't know what obstructive states are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all the way up to the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just refining the same principle of seeing the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... And it's important to see as well that everyone has that ability to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, for example, in some cases in suttas, these lay people who got enlightened seemingly instantaneously,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because of some magical event or luck that they had.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because, well, for whatever reason, it might be in their past lives or even in their present life, their satiety was not as proliferated, like they were not as constricted in that foreground level of attention, that they were able to see, to some extent, that peripheral domain, the back of your head, as I was saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the Buddha explains these things, they're actually able to see them concretely in their own experience here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the dhamma doesn't... if hearing about these things, the Four Noble Truths, craving, suffering, cessation of craving, and all these things, and you don't have the right view, that can only be because the sign of the mind, where those recognitions, that would allow those recognitions to land, is not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you make perfect
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see where that craving is, as I said, always behind you, that's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even though, yes, you agree with the fact that craving is suffering, because you read about it in the suttas, you won't... it won't lead to the inside of the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... everyone has that recognition at the side of the mind, on a basic level, to some degree, because otherwise you wouldn't be able to even start the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just that it not... it's not enough to, eh... to constitute the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could say like, you know, some people can't even catch themselves telling lies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's just... even if you tell them or whatever, they're just unable to recognize their own actions or not specifically things against the precepts, just anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just have... they operate almost like animals, let's say, without recollection and without any simultaneous awareness of the things they're doing while they're doing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that already shows you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And some other people, like, you know, they... very sharp faculties, like even though they haven't heard the dhamma, and they have a natural sense of self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the New Age sense of watching your knees and stuff, because nobody does that unless somebody has told them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas this is something that you would be almost ingrained into, whether you heard dhamma or not, this side of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that shows you that it's just a matter of cultivating it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something that you have to gain for the first time or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just furthering
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a good way to illustrate how seeing the signs of the mind would actually be necessary, even to purify your physical and verbal actions, would be, let's say you have an intention to do something that's externally good, or in a Buddhist sense, good, like visiting a monastery, having dhamma discussions, reading suttas, and then you might assume that that external property of that action is what determines it is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that actually it's the internal motivation behind it that determines it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that which can change from day to day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if one day you're doing that action because you crave for company, you were bored,
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to have a good time.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, it's rooted in passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that same action is actually unwholesome, even though other Buddhists might be praising you in account of it and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, it's exactly the same principle on the mental level, which is what the sutta is describing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the unskillful bhikkhu assumes that just thinking about the four-sixth pathanas, just contemplating these things and going through the motions, is good, failing to see that if it's driven by passion, aversion, and delusion,
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's the driving force for those contemplations, that whole situation becomes unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... you would get to see the signs of your mind in relation to actions on those... on any of those three domains, eh... not through quickness of awareness and developing sharp concentration and being able to catch the sequence of mind moments.
[SPEAKER_01]: But through self-honesty, even on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why if a person doesn't have that basic self-honesty, they can practice the dhamma for decades, they won't get the right view, because they won't be seeing the signs of their mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And seeing the signs of their mind would result in abandoning the first three fetters,
[SPEAKER_01]: As Anguttara Nikaya 668 says, because, for example, the assumption of virtue and practices, not just rites and rituals, as it's sometimes translated, is precisely rooted in failing to see that even these things that the Buddha factually talked about, the virtue and the beneficial external practices,
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, that doesn't mean that one shouldn't be virtuous, because it's more unwholesome not to be virtuous than to be virtuous with a wrong attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it just means that that's not enough in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not enough to just go through those motions and assume that that automatically means the mind is being purified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have we clarified sufficiently what the sign might be?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one more thing you might mention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you practically go about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The first thing you need to restrain is this tendency to, as I said, be expecting a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of the most...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually the simile the Buddha gave.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not asking yourself when is the axe handle gonna wear out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just using it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just using this axe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that at some point, it will have to wear out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not be the day after tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not even be next year.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not even be in two years.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know for sure that if you're using that axe, as opposed to leaving it there, the day where it's gonna wear, where you will recognize,
[SPEAKER_01]: That the axe handle is worn out, it's coming closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it... but...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's no doubt there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody knows that what they're doing is right.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not second-guessing whether they're actually wearing off this axe handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They know they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point being, if you're making this effort, you will... you are developing the recognition on the side of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, it's not something you have to wait for.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just refining some principle that's already there in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to wait for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mind is not coming and going.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, you know, getting better at, yeah, just exercising or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not expecting some magical day where, like, you already can lift 10 pounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, in one week, you will be able to lift 15 and then 20.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, none of those
[SPEAKER_01]: Milestones are more special than than the previous one.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the same thing developing further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... that that's the basically the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't know how many pounds you will be able to lift.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be able to lift to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be factually be able to see like in hindsight.
[SPEAKER_01]: That some progress has happened, even before the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be able to see... Now, I'm more able to see these subtle inclinations in mind that before I would have been totally unaware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you know that it's that same principle that if you take further, you know for sure, eventually, at that point, it will be enough for you to see the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's confirmation that you're going in the right direction, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because that's one of the main obstacles, this sort of attitude of wanting to achieve something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, I mean, it motivates you to practice, of course, but if you don't see that as a phenomenon, you just take it for granted and run with it and think that the practice, the results just happen to you, regardless of
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, what your attitudes towards those... that endeavor is, then it's never gonna come, because you're not doing the work that would actually make them come about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.